I worked on a film called "Apollo 13,"
عملت في فيلم "أبولو 13"
and when I worked on this film, I discovered something
وقد اكتشفت شيئًا حينها
about how our brains work, and how our brains work
عن كيفية عمل الدماغ
is that, when we're sort of infused with
وهو أنه عندما نكون في حالة
either enthusiasm or awe or fondness or whatever,
حماسة أو رعب أو هلع أو غيرها،
it changes and alters our perception of things.
فإن ذلك يغير ويؤثر على نظرتنا للأشياء.
It changes what we see. It changes what we remember.
إنه يغير ما نراه، وما نتذكره.
And as an experiment, because I dauntingly create
وكتجربة، لأني أخذت على عاتقي
a task for myself of recreating a Saturn V launch
مهمة محاكاة إطلاق صاروخ ساتورن 5
for this particular movie, because I put it out there,
لهذا الفيلم تحديدًا، وبما أنني التزمت بذلك،
I felt a little nervous about it, so I need to do an experiment
أحسـستُ ببعض التوتر، فأردت القيام بتجربة
and bring a group of people like this in a projection room
وأحضرتُ أشخاصا مثلكم لقاعة عرض
and play this stock footage, and when I played this
وقمت بعرض هذا المشاهد الخام،
stock footage, I simply wanted to find out
وحين عرضت هذه المشاهد الخام، أردت فقط معرفة
what people remembered, what was memorable about it?
ما يتذكره الناس، وما يستحق التذكر؟
What should I actually try to replicate?
ما ينبغي أن أحاول أن أركز عليه؟
What should I try to emulate to some degree?
وما ينبغي أن أحاكيه إلى حد ما؟
So this is the footage that I was showing everybody.
وهذه هي اللقطة التي عرضتها على الجميع.
And what I discovered is, because of the nature
واكتشفت أنه نظرا لطبيعة اللقطات
of the footage and the fact that we're doing this film,
ولأننا نعد هذا الفيلم،
there was an emotion that was built into it
أنها كانت تحمل أحاسيس منغرسة فيها
and our collective memories of what this launch meant to us
وفي ذاكرتنا الجماعية لما يعنيه لنا هذا الإطلاق
and all these various things.
وكل هذه الأشياء.
When I showed it, and I asked, immediately after
وسألت مباشرة بعد انتهاء عرضها،
the screening was over, what they thought of it,
عن رأيهم فيها،
what was your memorable shots, they changed them.
وعن اللقطات التي علقت بأذهانهم، غيروها.
They were -- had camera moves on them.
كانت هناك كاميرا تتحرك بداخلهم.
They had all kinds of things. Shots were combined,
كانت بداخلهم أشياءٌ عديدة، لقطات مختلفة.
and I was just really curious, I mean, what the hell
وقد كنت مستغربا بشدة، بحق السماء،
were you looking at just a few minutes ago
ما الذي كنتم نتظرون إليه للتو؟
and how come, how'd you come up with this sort of description?
من أين جئتم بوصفٍ كهذا لما شاهدتموه؟
And what I discovered is, what I should do is not actually
وما اكتشفته كان، أن ما عليَّ فعله في الواقع
replicate what they saw, is replicate what they remembered.
ليس تقليد ما رأوه، بل تقليد ما تذكروه.
So this is our footage of the launch, based on, basically,
هذه هي لقطة الإطلاق التي صوَّرناه،
taking notes, asking people what they thought, and then
بناءً على ملاحظات وآراء الناس،
the combination of all the different shots and all
ومن ثم جمع كافة اللقطات
the different things put together created their sort of
والأشياء المختلفة، للحصول على
collective consciousness of what they remembered
هذا الوعي الجماعي لما تذكروه.
it looked like, but not what it really looked like.
لكن ذلك ليس حقًا ما بدت عليه.
So this is what we created for "Apollo 13."
هذا ما ابتكرناه لأجل "أبولو 13".
(Launch noises)
(صوت الإطلاق)
So literally what you're seeing now is the confluence
ما ترونه الآن هو حرفيًا اجتماع
of a bunch of different people, a bunch of different memories,
لآراء أناس مختلفين، ولمجموعةٍ من الذكريات المختلفة،
including my own, of taking a little bit of liberty
ومنها رأيي أنا، مع القليل من الارتجال
with the subject matter.
بخصوص طبيعة الموضوع.
I basically shot everything with short lenses,
قمتُ بتصوير كل شيءٍ بعدسات قصيرة،
which means that you're very close to the action,
مما يعني بأنكم تكونون قريبين جدًا من المشهد،
but framed it very similarly to the long lens shots
لكن جعلنا اللقطات تبدو كأنها التقطت بعدسات طويلة المدى
which gives you a sense of distance, so I was basically
مما يعطيكم إحساسًا بالمسافة، لذلك ما كنت أقوم به أساسا
was setting up something that would remind you
هو إعداد شيء يمكنه أن يذكِّركم
of something you haven't really quite seen before. (Music)
بشيء لم تروه كثيرا من قبل (موسيقى)
And then I'm going to show you exactly what it is
وسأريكم بالضبط ما هو ذلك الشيء
that you were reacting to when you were reacting to it.
الذي كنتم تستجيبون له عندما كنتم تستجيبون له.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Tom Hanks: Hello, Houston, this is Odyssey.
توم هانكس: مرحبًا، هيوستن، هذه أدويسي.
It's good to see you again. (Cheers) (Music)
من الرائع رؤيتكم مرَّة أخرى (تهليل) (موسيقى)
Rob Legato: I pretend they're clapping for me.
روبرت ليغاتو: أفترض أنهم يصفِّقون لي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So now I'm in a parking lot. Basically it's a tin can,
أنا الآن في مرأب مكشوف. في الأصل هي علبة صفيح،
and I'm basically recreating the launch with
وما أفعله هو إعادة خلق لحظة الإطلاق باستعمال
fire extinguishers, fire, I have wax that I threw
مطافئ الحريق والنار وشمع لألقيه
in front of the lens to look like ice, and so basically
أمام العدسة ليبدو كالجليد،
if you believed any of the stuff that I just showed you,
لذا، إن صدقتم أي شيء مما أريتكم للتو،
what you were reacting to, what you're emoting to,
أو تفاعلتم معها أو حركت مشاعركم،
is something that's a total falsehood, and I found that
اعلموا أنها محض خدع، وأجد أن ذلك
really kind of fascinating.
أمر رائع حقًا.
And in this particular case, this is the climax of the movie,
وفي هذه الحالة تحديدًا، فإنَّ هذه هي ذروة الفيلم
and, you know, the weight of achieving it was simply
وفي الحقيقة لم يتطلب تصويرها جهدا كبيرا
take a model, throw it out of a helicopter, and shoot it.
خذ دمية، ارمها من على مروحيَّة، وصورها
And that's simply what I did.
وهذا ما قمتُ به بكل بساطة.
That's me shooting, and I'm a fairly mediocre operator,
هذا أنا أصور، وأنا مضبط إطار عادي،
so I got that nice sense of verisimilitude, of a kind of,
حصلت على ذلك الإحساس بتصديق
you know, following the rocket all the way down,
تتبع الصاروخ طوال الطريق
and giving that little sort of edge, I was desperately
وأن أقدم نوعا من الحدة، كنت أحاول يائسا
trying to keep it in frame. So then I come up to the next thing.
الحفاظ عليه داخل الإطار. وبعدها انتقلت للأمر التالي.
We had a NASA consultant who was actually an astronaut,
كان لدينا مستشار من الناسا هو رجل فضاء
who was actually on some of the missions, of Apollo 15,
عمل في بعض المهام بأبولو 15،
and he was there to basically double check my science.
وكان دوره التحقق من معرفتي العلمية.
And, I guess somebody thought they needed to do that.
وأعتقد أن أحدهم فكر بأنهم بحاجة لذلك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I don't know why, but they thought they did.
لا أعلم لم، لكنهم اعتقدوا بأنهم يحتاجون لذلك.
So we were, he's a hero, he's an astronaut, and
المهم، كان بطلا ورجل فضاء
we're all sort of excited, and, you know, I gave myself
وكنا جميعا متحمسين، فأظهرت ببعض الحرية
the liberty of saying, you know, some of the shots I did
إعجابي ببعض اللقطات التي صورتها
didn't really suck that bad.
والتي لم تكن سيئة.
And so maybe, you know, we were feeling kind of a little
وربما أننا كنا نشعر ببعض
good about it, so I brought him in here, and he needed
الارتياح بشأنها، لذا أخذته إلى هناك
to really check and see what we were doing,
فقد كان لابد أن يتحقق ويشاهد ما نفعله
and basically give us our A plus report card,
لكي يعطينا درجة ممتاز،
and so I showed him some shots we were working on,
لذا أريته بعض المشاهد التي كنا نعمل عليها،
and waiting for the reaction that you hope for,
وانتظرت ردة الفعل التي تنتظرونها،
which is what I got. (Music) (Launch noises)
والتي حصلت عليها. (موسيقى) (صوت الإطلاق)
So I showed him these two shots,
أريته هذين المشهدين،
and then he basically told me what he thought.
وأخبرني بعدها برأيه.
("That's wrong") (Laughter)
("هذا خطأ") (ضحك)
Okay. (Laughter)
حسنا! (ضحك)
It's what you dream about.
كان ذلك ما تحلمون به.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So what I got from him is, he turned to me and said,
أما ما حصلت عليه فهو، أنه التفت إلي قائلا،
"You would never, ever design a rocket like that.
"لا يجب أبدا أن تصمم صاروخا كهذا.
You would never have a rocket go up
ولن ينطلق أبدا هذا الصاروخ
while the gantry arms are going out. Can you imagine
أثناء تراجع الأذرع القنطرية. هل تتخيل
the tragedy that could possibly happen with that?
مدى المأساة التي قد تحدث بسبب ذلك؟
You would never, ever design a rocket like that."
لا يجب أبدا أن تصمم صاروخا كهذا."
And he was looking at me. It's like, Yeah, I don't know
وكان ينظر إلي. وأنأ أقول بداخلي،
if you noticed, but I'm the guy out in the parking lot
لا أعلم إن لاحظت لكني الرجل الذي أعاد تصوير
recreating one of America's finest moments with
أحد أهم لحظات أمريكا في مرآب مكشوف
fire extinguishers.
بواسطة طفايات الحريق.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I'm not going to argue with you. You're an astronaut,
وأنا لن أجادلك، فأنت رجل فضاء
a hero, and I'm from New Jersey, so --
وبطل وأنا من نيو جيرسي، لذا --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'm just going to show you some footage.
أنا سأريك بعض اللقطات وحسب.
I'm just going to show you some footage, and tell me what you think.
وأنت أخبرني برأيك فيها.
And then I did kind of get the reaction I was hoping for.
وبعدها حصلت على ردة الفعل التي انتظرت.
So I showed him this, and this is actual footage
أريته هذا، إنها اللقطات الأصلية
that he was on. This is Apollo 15. This was his mission.
للمهمة التي شارك فيها بأبولو 15.
So I showed him this, and the reaction I got was interesting.
ثم أريته هذا، وكانت ردة فعله مثيرة.
("That's wrong too.") (Laughter)
("هذا خطأ أيضا.") (ضحك)
So, and what happened was, I mean, what I sort of intuned
والذي حدث أني خلصت إلى
in that is that he remembered it differently.
أن ذكرياته كانت مختلفة.
He remembered that was a perfectly safe sort of gantry
كان يتذكر نظام قناطر وإطلاق صاروخ
system, perfectly safe rocket launch, because he's sitting
آمن تماما لأنه كان جالسا بصاروخ
in a rocket that has, like, a hundred thousand pounds
يزن ما يعادل 50 طن من قوة الدفع
of thrust, built by the lowest bidder.
مبني من طرف أقل مزايد.
He was hoping it was going to work out okay.
وكان يأمل بأنه سيعمل بشكل جيد.
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
So he twisted his memory around.
لذا غير ذكرياته عنه.
Now, Ron Howard ran into Buzz Aldrin, who was not
التقى رون هوارد ببز ألدرن، الذي لم يكن بالفيلم
on the movie, so he had no idea that we were faking
أي أنه لم يكن يعلم بأننا زيفنا
any of this footage, and he just responded
تلك اللقطات، لذا كان رده
as he would respond, and I'll run this.
كما يجب، لذا سأريكم هذا.
Ron Howard: Buzz Aldrin came up to me
رون هوارد: زارني بز ألدرن وقال
and said, "Hey, that launch footage, I saw some shots
"رأيت بعضا من لقطات الإطلاق التي
I'd never seen before. Did you guys, what vault did you find
لم أرها من قبل، في أي قبو عثرتم عليها؟
that stuff in?" And I said, "Well, no vault, Buzz,
فأجبت: "ليس هناك من قبو يا بز،
we generated all that from scratch."
لقد ابتكرنا كل ذلك من لا شيء."
And he said, "Huh, that's pretty good. Can we use it?"
فقال: "كان ذلك رائعا. هل يمكننا استخدامه؟"
(Explosion) ("Sure") (Laughter)
(صوت انفجار) ("بالطبع") (ضحك)
RL: I think he's a great American.
روبرت: إنه أمريكي رائع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, "Titanic" was, if you don't know the story,
لم تنته قصة "تيتانيك"،
doesn't end well.
إن لم تعرفوها، بشكل جيد.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Jim Cameron actually photographed the real Titanic.
الواقع أن جيمس كاميرون قد صور التيتانيك الحقيقي.
So he basically set up, or basically shattered
وهكذا أسس أو أسقط الجدار
the suspension of disbelief, because what he photographed
الماتع للتصديق، لأن ما صوره
was the real thing, a Mir sub going down, or actually
كان الشيء الحقيقي، بغواصة مير،
two Mir subs going down to the real wreck,
أو في الواقع أرسل اثنتين إلى الحطام،
and he created this very haunting footage.
وصور هذا المشهد الساحر.
It's really beautiful, and it conjures up all these
إنه رائع، ويجعل كل تلك المشاعر
various different emotions, but he couldn't photograph
المختلفة تطفو إلى السطح، لكنه لم يتمكن
everything, and to tell the story,
من تصوير كل شيء، والحقيقة كان علي
I had to fill in the gaps, which is now rather daunting,
ملء الفراغات، وكانت مهمة صعبة،
because now I have to recreate back to back
لأنه كان علي إعادة التصوير لحظة بلحظة
what really happened and I had, I'm the only one
وهذا ما حدث، وكنت الوحيد
who could really blow it at that point.
القادر على تدمير كل شيء.
So this is the footage he photographed,
هذا هو المشهد الذي صوره،
and it was pretty moving and pretty awe-inspiring.
وكان جد مؤثر وجد مذهل.
So I'm going to just let it run, so you kind of absorb
سأترككم مع المشهد، لتستوعبوه
this sort of thing, and I'll describe my sort of reactions
وسأصف بعدها مشاعري
when I was looking at it for the very first time.
عند مشاهدتي له لأول مرة.
I got the feeling that my brain wanted to basically
كان لدي إحساس بأن دماغي يرغب
see it come back to life.
في رؤية السفينة تعود للحياة.
I automatically wanted to see this ship,
وأردت بشكل تلقائي رؤية،
this magnificent ship, basically in all its glory,
تلك السفينة العظيمة، في قمة مجدها،
and conversely, I wanted to see it not in all its glory,
وفي نفس الوقت، أردت رؤيتها دون مجدها،
basically go back to what it looks like.
أي العودة إلى ما تبدو عليه الآن.
So I conjured up an effect that I'm later going to show you
لذا صممت التأثير الذي سأريكم بعد قليل
what I tried to do, which is kind of the heart of the movie,
الهدف منه، وهو في رأيي جوهرالفيلم،
for me, and so that's why I wanted to do the movie,
والسبب وراء رغبتي في العمل به،
that's why I wanted to create the sort of things I created.
وتصميم المؤثرات التي صممتها.
And I'll show you, you know, another thing that I found
وسأريكم أمرا آخر أثار انتباهي
interesting is what we really were emoting to
وهو ما يثير مشاعرنا حقا
when you take a look at it.
عند مشاهدتكم للفيلم.
So here's the behind the scenes, a couple of little shots here.
هذه كواليس المشاهد، بضعة لقطات صغيرة.
So, when you saw my footage,
عندما كنتم تشاهدون مقطعيَّ،
you were seeing this: basically, a bunch of guys
شاهدتم هذا: مجموعة من الأشخاص
flipping a ship upside down, and the little Mir subs
يقلبون سفينة رأسا على عقب
are actually about the size of small footballs,
وغواصتي مير صغيرتين بحجم كرة قدم،
and shot in smoke.
صورت في الدخان.
Jim went three miles went down, and I went about
غاص جيمس 5 كلم بينما مشيت أنا
three miles away from the studio
حوالي 3 كلم خارج الاستوديو
and photographed this in a garage.
وصورت ذلك في كراج.
And so, but what you're emoting to, or what you're looking
ولكن ما يثير مشاعركم وما تشاهدونه،
at, had the same feeling, the same haunting quality,
يثير نفس الإحساس لديكم ونفس السحر،
that Jim's footage had, so I found it so fascinating
هذا مقطع جيمس، وما أدهشني
that our brains sort of, once you believe something's real,
أن أدمغتنا فور تصديقها لحقيقة شيء ما،
you transfer everything that you feel about it,
تجعلنا نحس بكل المشاعر المرتبطة بها،
this quality you have, and it's totally artificial.
هذا الشعور الذي لديكم، مع أنه ليس طبيعيا.
It's totally make-believe, yet it's not to you,
فهو متخيل لكن ليس بنظركم أنتم،
and I found that that was a very interesting thing
وهذا ما أثار اهتمامي لاستكشافه واستخدامه
to explore and use, and it caused me to create the next
وهو ما جعلني أصمم التأثير التالي
effect that I'll show you, which is
الذي سأريكم، وهو عبارة عن انتقال سحري،
this sort of magic transition, and all I was really attempting
وجل ما كنت أحاول القيام به
to do is basically have the audience cue the effect,
هو الحصول على الإشارة من الجمهور،
so it became a seamless experience for them,
لتكون تجربة سلسة بالنسبة لهم،
that I wasn't showing you my sort of interpretation,
حيث لم أكن أريكم تأويلي الخاص،
I was showing you what you wanted to see.
بل ما ترغبون في مشاهدته.
And the very next shot, right after this --
المشهد القادم بعد هذا --
So you can see what I was doing.
يمكنكم مشاهدة ما كنت أفعله.
So basically, if there's two subs in the same shot,
الحقيقة، أن أي مشهد بغواصتين كان
I shot it, because where's the camera coming from?
من تصويري، لأنه من أين تصور الكاميرا؟
And when Jim shot it, it was only one sub,
وإذا كان من تصوير جيمس، ستشاهدون
because he was photographing from the other,
غواصة واحدة، لكونه يصور من الأخرى،
and I don't remember if I did this or Jim did this.
ولا أذكر إن كنت صاحب هذا المشهد أم جيمس.
I'll give it to Jim, because he could use the pat on the back.
سأنسبه لجيمس، لأنه بحاجة للتشجيع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Okay. So now the Titanic transition.
لنشاهد الآن انتقال المشاهد في التيتانيك.
So this is what I was referring to where I wanted to basically
هذا ما كنت ألمح إليه عندما كنت أقول بأني أرغب
magically transplant from one state of the Titanic
في انتقال سحري من حالة تيتانيك إلى أخرى.
to the other. So I'll just play the shot once. (Music)
سأريكم مرة واحدة المشهد. (موسيقى)
(Music)
(موسيقى)
And what I was hoping for is that it just melts in front of you.
ما كنت أرجوه هو أن يذوب المشهد أمام أعينكم.
Gloria Stuart: That was the last time Titanic ever saw daylight.
غلوريا ستيوارت: هذه آخر مرة رأت التيتانيك ضوء النهار.
RL: So, what I did is basically I had another
روبرت: قمت بإعادة تجربة قاعة العرض
screening room experience where I was basically tracking
بحيث سجلت هذه المرة
where I was looking, or where we were looking,
المكان الذي كنا ننظر إليه في الشاشة
and of course you're looking at the two people on the bow
وبالطبع كنتم تنظرون إلى الشخصين بمقدمة السفينة
of the ship, and then at some point,
وبعدها عند نقطة ما،
I'm changing the periphery of the shot,
غيرت محيط المشهد،
I'm changing, it's becoming the rusted wreck,
ليتحول إلى الحطام الصدئ،
and then I would run it every day, and then I would find
ثم بدأت أشاهده يوميا، إلى أن عثرت
exactly the moment that I stopped looking at them
على اللحظة التي أتوقف فيها عن النظر إليهم
and start noticing the rest of it, and the moment
وأنظر لما يحيط بهما، وقمنا بتحديد
my eye shifted, we just marked it to the frame.
لحظة تحرك عيناي على الصورة الجزئية.
The moment my eye shifted, I immediately started
وفور تحركهما، بدأت بتغييرهما،
to change them, so now somehow you missed
بحيث لا تستطيعون معرفة
where it started and where it stopped.
متى بدأ ومتى توقف.
And so I'll just show it one more time.
سأريكم المشهد مرة أخرى. (موسيقى)
(Music) And it's literally done by using what our brains
وقد أنجز المشهد باستخدام ما تفعله أدمغتنا
naturally do for us, which is, as soon as you shift
طبيعيا من أجلنا، أي فور تشتت انتباهكم
your attention, something changes, and then I left
يتغير شيء ما وأترك الوشاح
the little scarf going, because it really wanted to be
لأنه مشهد يجب أن يكون طيفيا
a ghostly shot, really wanted to feel like they were still
ليبدو وكأنهما ما يزالان على الحطام.
on the wreck, essentially. That's where they were buried forever.
هذا هو ملاذهما الأخير والأبدي.
Or something like that. I just made that up.
أو شيء من هذا القبيل، أصبحت رومنسيا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It was, incidentally, the last time I ever saw daylight.
وبالمناسبة، كانت هذه آخر مرة رأيتُ فيها ضوء النهار.
It was a long film to work on. (Laughter)
كان فيلما طويلا للعمل عليه. (ضحك)
Now, "Hugo" was another interesting movie, because
كان "هيوغو" فيلما مثيرا أيضا
the movie itself is about film illusions.
لأن الفيلم نفسه يتحدث عن الخدع السينمائية.
It's about how our brain is tricked into seeing a persistence
ويتحدث كيف أن دماغنا ينخدع بمشهد
of vision that creates a motion picture,
قادر على خلق صورة متحركة.
and one of the things I had to do is, we —
ومن الأمور التي كان علي القيام بها هي، أننا--
Sasha Baron Cohen is a very clever, very smart guy,
ساشا بارون كوهين هو شخص ذكي جدا
comedian, wanted to basically do an homage to the kind of
وممثل فكاهي، أراد أن يكرم
the Buster Keaton sort of slapstick things, and he wanted
باستر كيتون والفكاهة الهزلية
his leg brace to get caught on a moving train.
بأن تعلق جبيرته بقطار متحرك.
Very dangerous, very impossible to do, and particularly
وذلك أمر خطير، ويستحيل فعله، ولاسيما
on our stage, because there literally is no way to actually
حيث نصور، لأنه يستحيل في الحقيقة تحريك القطار
move this train, because it fits so snugly into our set.
لأنه مركب بدقة على مكان التصوير.
So let me show you the scene, and then I basically
لذا دعوني أريكم المشهد،
used the trick that was identified by Sergei Eisenstein,
استخدمت فكرة سيرجي آيزنشتاين،
which is, if you have a camera that's moving with a moving
إذا كانت لديك كاميرا تتحرك مع شيء متحرك
object, what is not moving appears to be moving,
فإن الجماد يبدو كأنه يتحرك
and what is moving appears to be stopped,
بينما تبدو الأشياء المتحركة وكأنها جامدة،
so what you're actually seeing now is the train is not
في الواقع ما تنظرون إليه الآن هو قطار
moving at all, and what is actually moving is the floor.
ثابت لأن الأرضية هي من تتحرك،
So this is the shot. That's a little video of
وهذا هو المشهد. وهذا فيديو قصير
what you're looking at there, which is our little test,
لما تشاهدونه هنا، وهو اختبارنا الصغير،
so that's actually what you're seeing, and I thought it was
وهذا ما تشاهدونه في الحقيقة، ففكرت بأنها
sort of an interesting thing, because it was, part
فكرة مثيرة، لأنها كانت
of the homage of the movie itself is coming up with this
جزء من تكريم الفيلم نفسه.
sort of genius trick which I can't take credit for.
والتي لا أستطيع أن أنسبها لنفسي،
I'd love to but I can't, because it was invented
مع أنني وددت لو أنها فكرتي لكن ليس كذلك
like in 1910 or something like that, is I told Marty,
لانها ابتكرت في 1910، وأخبرت مارتي
and it's kind of one of those mind things that it's
بأنها نوع من ألعاب العقل التي يصعب
really hard to really get until you actually see it work,
فعلا فهمها ما لم تشاهد كيف تعمل،
and I said, you know, what I was going to do, and he said,
وقلت له: هل تعلم ما الذي سأفعله،
"So, let me see if I can get this straight. The thing with the wheels?
فقال: "لنرى إن كنتُ قد فهمتُ كل شيء، صاحب العجلات؟
That doesn't move."
هو من لا يتحرك."
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
"And the thing without the wheels, that moves."
"والأشياء الأخرى بدونها هي من تتحرك."
Precisely. (Laughter)
تماما. (ضحك)
Brings me to the next, and final --
وهذا ما ينقلني للموضوع القادم والأخير--
Marty's not going to see this, is he? (Laughter)
لن يشاهد مارتي هذه المحادثة، أليس كذلك؟ (ضحك)
This isn't viewed outside of -- (Laughter)
لن تبث هذه المحادثة-- (ضحك)
The next illustration is something that, there's like
التوضيح التالي هو، كنظرية الطلقة الواحدة،
all one shot theory. It's a very elegant way of telling a story,
وهي طريقة منمقة للإخبار بقصة،
especially if you're following somebody on a journey,
ولاسيما وأنت تتبع شخصا ما يتحرك
and that journey basically tells something about
وأن تلك الحركة تخبر بشيء ما
their personality in a very concise way,
عن شخصيته بطريقة موجزة،
and what we wanted to do based on the shot in "Goodfellas,"
بينما يرتكز ما نود القيام به على مشهد بفيلم
which is one of the great shots ever,
"الأصدقاء الطيبون" وهو من أعظم المشاهد على الإطلاق،
a Martin Scorsese film, of basically following Henry Hill
وهو فيلم لمارتن سكورسيزي، عن هنري هيل
through what it feels like to be a gangster walk
وعن الشعور بأن تكون رجل عصابة يمشي
going through the Copacabana and being treated in a special way.
بكوباكابانا ويعامل بشكل خاص.
He was the master of his universe, and we wanted Hugo
كان سيد عالمه وكنا بحاجة لهيوغو
to feel the same way, so we created this shot.
لكي نشعر بنفس الشيء، لذا صورنا هذا المشهد.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
That's Hugo. (Music)
هذا هيوغو، (موسقى)
And we felt that if we could basically move the camera
واعتقدنا أنه إن حركنا الكاميرا معه
with him, we would feel what it feels like to be this boy
فسنحس بما يحس به ذلك الطفل
who is basically the master of his universe,
الذي هو في الأساس سيد عالمه،
and his universe is, you know, behind the scenes
وعالمه كما تعلمون موجود خلف الكواليس
in the bowels of this particular train station
داخل محطة القطار تلك
that only he can actually navigate through
الوحيد القادر على العبور بتلك الطريقة،
and do it this way, and we had to make it feel that
وكان يجب أن يبدو الأمر طبيعيا،
this is his normal, everyday sort of life,
كحياته اليومية،
so the idea of doing it as one shot was very important,
لذا كان من المهم القيام بذلك في مشهد واحد،
and of course, in shooting in 3D, which is basically
وبالطبع، في مشهد ثلاثي الأبعاد، مما يعني
it's a huge camera that's hanging off of a giant stick,
كاميرا ضخمة معلقة بذراع تحريك ضخم،
so to recreate a steadycam shot was the task,
وذلك بهدف خلق تأثير الكاميرا الثابتة
and make it feel kind of like what the reaction you got
وجعله يخلق لديكم نفس الشعور الذي كان لديكم
when you saw the "Goodfellas" shot.
عندما شاهدتم مشهد "الأصدقاء الطيبون".
So what you're now going to see is how we actually did it.
ما ستشاهدونه الآن هو طريقة تصويره.
It's actually five separate sets shot at five different times
في الواقع هو 5 مسارح منفصلة في 5 أوقات مختلفة
with two different boys.
بطفلين اثنين.
The one on the left is where the shot ends,
الأول على اليسار حيث ينتهي المشهد
and the shot on the right is where it takes over,
والثاني على اليمين حيث ينوب عنه،
and now we switch boys, so it went from Asa Butterfield,
وهنا حيث نستبدل الطفلين، من أسا بترفيلد،
who's the star of the show, to his stand-in. (Music)
وهو بطل الفيلم، لبديله. (موسيقى)
I wouldn't say his stunt double. There's a crazy rig
وهو ليس ببديل للمشاهد الخطرة.
that we built for this. (Music)
وقد صممنا ديكورا رائعا لذلك. (موسيقى)
And so this is, and now this is set number three
نتواجد الآن بالمسرح رقم 3
we're into, and then we're going to go into, basically
وسنمر بعدها إلى
the very last moment of the shot is actually
اللحظة الأخيرة بالمشهد المصور في الواقع
the steadycam shot. Everything else was shot on cranes
بكاميرا ثابتة. بينما صور الباقي برافعات
and various things like that, and it literally was done
وأشياء أخرى مشابهة، وقد تم ذلك
over five different sets, two different boys, different times,
على 5 مسارح، وبطفلين، وأوقات مختلفة،
and it all had to feel like it was all one shot, and what was
وكان يجب أن يبدو كل ذلك كمشهد واحد،
sort of great for me was it was probably
والجميل، أن ذلك المشهد كان على الأرجح
the best-reviewed shot I've ever worked on,
المفضل لدي على الإطلاق،
and, you know, I was kind of proud of it when I was done,
وكنت فخورا جدا بالنتيجة،
which is, you should never really be proud of stuff, I guess.
رغم أني أظن أنه لا يجب الافتخار بتلك الأمور،
So I was kind of proud of it, and I went to a friend of mine,
كنت فخورا به وذهبت عند صديق لي،
and said, "You know, this is, you know, kind of
وقلت له: "أتعلم، هذا من المشاهد المفضلة لدي،
the best-reviewed shot I've ever worked on.
من بين تلك التي عملت عليها.
What do you think was the reason?"
في رأيك ما السبب في ذلك؟"
And he said, "Because no one knows
فأجاب: "لأن لا أحد يعرف
you had anything to do with it."
بأنك عملت عليه."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, all I can say is, thank you,
كل ما يمكنني قوله هو شكرا لكم،
and that's my presentation for you. (Applause)
كان هذا هو عرضي لكم. (تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)